Love is a force of nature.
Brokeback Mountain is a drama, romance film directed by Ang Lee.
In 1960s Wyoming, two men develop a strong emotional and sexual relationship that endures as a lifelong
connection complicating their lives as they get married and start families of their own.
Ennis Del Mar, played by Heath Ledger.
Jack Twist, played by Jake Gyllenhaal.
Alma Beers, played by Michelle Williams.
Lureen Newsome, played by Anne Hathaway.
Joe Aguirre, played by Randy Quaid.
Cassie Cartwright, played by Linda Cardellini.
Brokeback Mountain is a 2005 American neo-Western romantic drama film
directed by Ang Lee and produced by Diana Ossana and James Schamus.
Adapted from the 1997 short story by Annie Proulx, the
screenplay was written by Ossana and Larry McMurtry.
The film stars Heath Ledger, Jake Gyllenhaal, Anne
Hathaway, and Michelle Williams.
Its plot depicts the complex romantic relationship between two American cowboys,
Ennis Del Mar and Jack Twist, in the American West from 1963 to 1983.
Lee became attached to the project in 2001 after previous attempts to
adapt Proulx's story into a film did not materialize.
Focus Features and River Road Entertainment would
jointly produce and distribute the film.
After Ledger and Gyllenhaal's casting was announced in 2003, filming
commenced in various locations in Alberta in 2004.
Brokeback Mountain premiered at the 2005 Venice International Film Festival, where it won
the Golden Lion, and was released to theaters on December 9 that year.
The film received widespread critical acclaim, with high praise
for the performances of Ledger and Gyllenhaal.
It emerged as a commercial success at the box-office, grossing over $178 million
worldwide against its $14 million budget, and won various accolades.
At the 78th Academy Awards, Brokeback Mountain was nominated for Best Picture and
won for Best Director, Best Adapted Screenplay, and Original Score.
It garnered seven nominations at the 63rd Golden Globe Awards, winning Best
Motion Picture — Drama, Best Director, Best Screenplay and Best Song.
At the 59th British Academy Film Awards, Brokeback Mountain had nine nominations, winning Best
Film, Best Direction, Best Adapted Screenplay and Best Supporting Actor (Gyllenhaal).
It was the film that topped the best of the year lists.
Brokeback Mountain was subject to controversies; its loss to Crash (2004) for the Academy Award for Best Picture,
subsequent censorship, and criticism from conservative media outlets received significant attention.
The sexuality of the main characters has been subject to discussion.
Brokeback Mountain has also been regarded as a turning point for
the advancement of queer cinema into the mainstream.
In 2018, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically, or
aesthetically significant" and was listed on the ballot for the American Film Institute's list of AFI's 100 Years...100 Movies (10th Anniversary Edition).
Since then, it has been ranked by several publications, film critics and scholars as
one of the best films of the 2000s, the 21st century and of all time.
The film explores themes of secret love, wyoming, usa,
countryside, homophobia, marriage crisis.
The tone is emotional.